<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="../../config/documentation-stylesheet.xml"?>
<!DOCTYPE isbdocument [
  <!ENTITY % AppConfig SYSTEM "../config/AppConfig.dtd">
  %AppConfig;

<!ENTITY javaURL "&webBaseURL;/&localJavaLibraryName;">
   ]>

<!--
  Copyright (C) 2003 by Institute for Systems Biology,
  Seattle, Washington, USA.  All rights reserved.
  
  This document is distributed under the GNU Lesser 
  General Public License, the text of which is available at:
    http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html
 -->

<!-- ========== PREAMBLE ========== -->

<isb:document xmlns:isb="http://www.systemsbiology.org/xmlns"
              xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1"
              xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1">

<isb:doctitle>&appName; Home Page</isb:doctitle>
<isb:docowner>&appMaintainerFullName;, &appMaintainerAffiliation;</isb:docowner>
<isb:docdate>$Date$</isb:docdate>
<isb:docowneremail>&appMaintainerEmailSafe;</isb:docowneremail>

<p>
Pointillist v2 is a set of MATLAB codes for inferring the set of
elements affected by a perturbation of a biological system, based on
multiple types of evidence.  
The software implements the full set of
data integration methods discussed in the article 
</p><blockquote>
<table border="1">
<tbody><tr><td>
Hwang&nbsp;D, Rust&nbsp;AG, Ramsey&nbsp;S, Smith&nbsp;JJ,
Leslie&nbsp;DM, Weston&nbsp;AD, de&nbsp;Atauri&nbsp;P,
Aitchison&nbsp;JD, Hood&nbsp;L, Siegel&nbsp;AF, Bolouri&nbsp;H.
"A data integration methodology for systems biology."
Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 2005; 102(48) 17296-17301.
</td></tr>
</tbody></table>
</blockquote>
<p></p>
<p>
The most recent version of the Pointillist v2 MATLAB codes is 2.1.2.
In addition, a Java implementation of an earlier version of our
nonparametric method (with the Fisher method) is available.  We are
presently adapting our Java version to conform to the method outlined
in the above articles, but the Java version should give equivalent
results to the MATLAB version on most datasets.
</p>

<table border="0">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<ul>
<li>
<a href="2.1.2/point212.zip">Download Pointillist v2.1.2</a> [1.4 MB ZIP archive of MATLAB codes] [This version includes Fisher's method, the Mudholkar-George
method, and the Liptak-Stouffer method, as described in the above article.  In
addition, v2.1.2 fixes some minor issues with the previous version.]
<a href="2.1.2/README.txt">[README]</a>
<p>
&nbsp;
</p>
</li>


<li>
<a href="1.0.1/installer/Web_Installers/install.htm">Download Java version of Pointillist's nonparametric method</a> [This 
version implements the nonparametric method and uses the weighted Fisher's
method, as decribed in the above article.] <br />
<a href="docs/UserManual.html">User Manual for Java version (html)</a><br />
<a href="docs/UserManual.pdf">User Manual for Java version (pdf, 244 kB)</a>
<p>
&nbsp;
</p>
</li>

<li>
<a href="docs/OldVersions.html">Go to download page for old versions of the
code</a>
</li>
</ul>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>


<p>
<b>Download counter:</b> Pointillist has been downloaded over <img src="images/PointillistDownloads.jpg" alt="[COUNTER]" align="middle" border="1" /> times since June 6, 2004.
</p>

<p>
<b>Visitor counter:</b> this page has been visited over <img src="images/PointillistVisitors.jpg" alt="[COUNTER]" align="middle" border="1" /> times since June 6, 2004.
</p>
<p>
The development of Pointillist is supported by grants from the National Science Foundation (NSF)
and the National Institutes of Health (NIH).
</p>

</isb:document>
