<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="../config/documentation-stylesheet.xml"?>
<!DOCTYPE Overview [
  <!ENTITY % CommonConfig SYSTEM "../config/CommonConfig.dtd">
  %CommonConfig;
  <!ENTITY internalWebServerURL "http://sun01.systemsbiology.net">
   ]>

<isb:document xmlns:isb="http://www.systemsbiology.org/xmlns">

<isb:doctitle>Resources Page:  Software, Publications, and News</isb:doctitle>
<isb:docauthor>&mainGroup;, &mainAffiliation;</isb:docauthor>

<isb:doccontents />

<isb:docsection name="Software Tools" label="software">

<p>
This section lists selected software tools that were (or are being) developed in collaboration
with Hamid Bolouri:
<ul>
<li><a href="Dizzy/">Dizzy, a chemical simulation program</a>&nbsp;&nbsp;[contains an <a href="javadoc/isb/chem/package-summary.html" target="_new">implementation</a> of the Gillespie stochastic simulator</li>
<li><a href="http://strc.herts.ac.uk/bio/maria/NetBuilder">NetBuilder</a> (Hertfordshire, UK)</li>
<li><a href="javadoc/">Java classes developed by the &mainGroup;</a></li>
</ul>
</p>

</isb:docsection>

<isb:docsection name="Links to Related Web Sites" label="links">

<p>
<ul>
<li><a href="&mainPublicURL;">&mainAffiliation; Home Page</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.cytoscape.org">Cytoscape home page</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.sbw-sbml.org" target="_new">Systems Biology Workbench</a> (Pasadena, CA USA)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.sbw-sbml.org" target="_new">Systems Biology Markup Language</a> (Pasadena, CA USA)</li>
</ul>
</p>

</isb:docsection>

<isb:docsection name="Active Collaborations" label="collaborations">

<p>
Our group has ongoing research collaborations with 
other labs and organizations outside of the &mainAffiliation;:
</p>
<p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://strc.herts.ac.uk/bio" target="_new">Biocomputation Group, University of Hertfordshire</a> (Hertfordshire, UK)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.sbw-sbml.org" target="_new">Systems Biology Workbench Development Group, Caltech</a> (Pasadena, CA, USA)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.cco.caltech.edu/~mirsky" target="_new">Davidson Lab, Caltech</a> (Pasadena, CA,USA)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.symbio.jst.go.jp" target="_new">ERATO Kitano Symbiotic Systems Project</a> (Tokyo, Japan)</li>
</ul>
</p>
</isb:docsection>

<isb:docsection name="Selected Publications" label="publications">

<p>
This section lists selected publications from members of the &mainGroup;.  
For a more comprehensive list of publications for a particular group member,
please refer to the individual&apos;s home page.  Copies of publications 
are available by request from Susan Harbison 
(<code>sharbison at systemsbiology.org</code>).
</p>
<p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#publications-pr-articles">peer-reviewed articles</a></li>
<li><a href="#publications-npr-articles">non-peer-reviewed articles</a></li>
<li><a href="#publications-editorials">editorials and reviews</a></li>
<li><a href="#publications-bookchapters">book chapters, monographs</a></li>
<li><a href="#publications-books">books</a></li>
</ul>
</p>


<isb:docsubsection name="Peer-reviewed scientific articles" label="publications-pr-articles">
<p>
<ol>
        <li>
        Clamp M, Andrews D et al, Ensembl 2002: Accommodating Comparative Genomics,
        <em>Nucleic Acids</em>, Jan 1;31(1), 38-42, 2003</li>
        <li>
        Mouse Genome Sequencing Consortium, Initial Sequencing and Comparative Analysis 
        of the Mouse Genome,<em>Nature</em>, Dec 5;420(6915), 520-562, 2002</li>
        <li>
        Rust A G, Mongin E, and Birney E, Genome Annotation Techniques: New Approaches 
        and Challenges, <em>Drug Discovery Today</em>, May 6;Vol.7, No.11, S70-76, 2002</li>
        <li>
        Hubbard T, Barker D et al,  The Ensembl Genome Database Project,
        <em>Nucleic Acids Research</em>, Jan 1;Vol.30, No.1, 38-41, 2002</li>
        <li>
        Schilstra, M J, Rust A G, Adams R, and Bolouri H,
        A Finite State Automaton Model for Multi-Neuron Simulations,
        <em>Neurocomputing</em>, 44-46, 1141-1148, 2002
        </li>
	<li>
	Hamid Bolouri and Eric H. Davidson,
	Modeling transcriptional regulatory networks, BioEssays 24.12, Dec.
	2002, pp.1118-1129.
        </li>
	<li>
	Eric H. Davidson, Jonathan P. Rast,
	Paola Oliveri, R. Andrew Cameron, Andrew Ransick, Chiou-Hwa Yuh,
	Cristina Calestani, Gabriele Amore, Veronica Hinman, Takuya
	Minokawa, C&eacute;sar Arenas-Mena, Ochan Otim, C. Titus Brown,
	Carolina Livi, Pei-yun Lee, Roger Revilla, Peter J. C. Clarke,
	Alistair Rust, Maria Schilstra, Jhengjun Pan, David R. McClay, Maria
	I. Arnone, Lee Rowan, Leroy E. Hood and Hamid Bolouri, A Genomic
	Regulatory Network for Development, <em>Science</em>, vol. 295, 1
	March 2002, pp.1669-1678
        </li>
	<li>
	Hamid Bolouri and Eric H. Davidson, 
	Modeling DNA sequence_based <em>cis</em>-regulatory gene networks,
	<em>Developmental Biology</em>, vol. 246, pp.2-13, June 2002
        </li>
	<li>
	C.T. Brown, A.G. Rust, M.J.
	Schilstra, Z. Pan, T. de Buysscher, P.J.C. Clarke, G. Griffin, E.H.
	Davidson and H. Bolouri, New computational approaches for
	computational-experimental analysis of <em>cis</em>-regulatory
	networks, <em>Developmental Biology</em>, vol. 246, pp.86-102, June
	2002
        </li>
	<li>
	Eric H. Davidson, Jonathan P. Rast,
	Paola Oliveri, R. Andrew Cameron, Andrew Ransick, Chiou-Hwa Yuh,
	Cristina Calestani, Gabriele Amore, Veronica Hinman, Takuya
	Minokawa, C&eacute;sar Arenas-Mena, Ochan Otim, C. Titus Brown,
	Carolina Livi, Pei-yun Lee, Roger Revilla, Peter J. C. Clarke,
	Alistair Rust, Maria Schilstra, Jhengjun Pan, David R. McClay, Maria
	I. Arnone, Lee Rowan, Leroy E. Hood and Hamid Bolouri, A Provisional
	Regulatory Gene Network for Specification of Endomesoderm in the Sea
	Urchin Embryo, <em>Developmental Biology</em>, , vol. 246, pp.162-190,
	June 2002</li>
	<li>
	See also report in <em>Science</em>
	Vol. 293, 3 August 2001, pp.788-789</li>
	<li>
	Morohashi M, Winn AE, Borisuk MT,
	Bolouri H, Doyle JC, Kitano H, Robustness as a measure of
	plausibility in models of biochemical networks, <em>Journal of
	Theoretical Biology</em>, vol. 216, Issue 1, 7 May 2002, pp 19-30</li>
	<li>
	Schilstra M.J., Rust A.G., Adams
	R.G., Bolouri H., A finite state automaton model for multi-neuron
	simulations,  <em>Neurocomputing</em>, vol. 44-46, June 2002, pp.
	1141-1148</li>
	<li>
	Hucka M, Finney A, Sauro H, Bolouri
	H, Doyle J, Kitano H, The ERATO Systems Biology Workbench: Enabling
	interaction and exchange between software tools for computational
	Biology, Proc. <em>Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</em>, pp.450-461,
	2002.</li>
	<li>
	Hucka M, Finney A, Sauro H, Bolouri
	H, Doyle J, Kitano H, The ERATO Systems Biology Workbench:
	architectural evolution, <em>Proc. Int. Conf. on Systems Biology</em>
	2001, pp.352-361</li>
	<li>
	Yuh CH, Bolouri H, Davidson EH,
	<em>Cis</em>-regulatory logic in the Endo16 gene: switching from a
	specification to a differentiation mode of control, <em>Development ,
	</em>128, pp.617-629, 2001</li>
	<li>
	Finney A, Hucka M, Sauro H, Bolouri
	H, Doyle J, Kitano H, An overview of the ERATO Systems Biology
	Workbench project, Proc. 2nd Workshop on <em>Computation of
	Biochemical Pathways</em>, European Media Labs, Heidelberg, Eds.
	Gauges R, van Gend C, Kummer U, pp.115-122, 2001</li>
	<li>
	Hucka M, Finney A, Sauro H, Bolouri
	H, Doyle J, Kitano H, The ERATO Systems Biology Workbench: An
	Integrated Environment for Multiscale and Multitheoretic
	Simulations, in Systems Biology, Chapter 6, <em>Foundations of
	Systems Biology</em>, ed. Hiroaki Kitano, MIT Press, 2001</li>
	<li>
	Morohashi M, Hucka, M, Sauro HM, 
	Finney AM, Bolouri H, Doyle JC, and Kitano H, The Systems Biology
	Workbench, in Japanese, Chapter 1 in <em>Development of Systems
	Biology</em> by Hiroaki Kitano, Sprinter-Verlag Tokyo, pp.25-36. 2001</li>
	<li>
	Sabisch T, Ferguson A &amp; Bolouri
	H, Identification of Complex Shapes Using a Self-Organising Neural
	System , <em>IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks</em>, Vol. 11, No.
	4, pp921-934, 2000</li>
	<li>
	Rust AG, Adams R &amp; Bolouri H,
	Evolutionary Neural Topiary: Growing and Sculpting Artificial
	Neurons to Order, Proc.of 7th Int. Conf. on the <em>Simulation and
	Synthesis of Living Systems</em>, MIT Press, 146-150, 2000 
	</li>
	<li>
	Pan Z, Rust AG, &amp; Bolouri H,
	Image Redundancy Reduction for Neural Network Classification using
	Discrete Cosine Transforms, Procs. of the <em>IEEE-INNS-ENNS,
	International Joint Conference on Neural Networks</em> (IJCNN&apos;2000) ,
	Vol. III, 149-154, Como, Italy, 2000 
	</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H, Mechanisms Underlying the
	Evolution of Robust Nonlinear Control in Biology, Proc. of <em>IEEE
	International Symposium on Intelligent Control/Intelligent Systems
	and Semiotics</em>, IEEE, 441-446, 1999 
	</li>
	<li>
	Pan Z, Sabisch T, Adams R &amp;
	Bolouri H, Staged Training of Neocognitron by Evolutionary
	Algorithms, Proc. of <em>IEEE Congress on Evolutionary Computation</em>
	(CEC&apos;99), 1965-1972, Washington D.C, July 6-9, 1999</li>
	<li>
	Yuh C W, Bolouri H &amp; Davidson E
	H, Genomic Cis-Regulatory Logic: Experimental and Computational
	Analysis of a Sea Urchin Gene, <em>Science</em>, Vol 279, No. 5358,
	pp1896-1902, 20 March 1998</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H, Adams R, George S &amp;
	Rust A G, Molecular Self-Organisation in a Developmental Model for
	the Evolution of Large-Scale Artificial Neural Network Proc. <em>Int.
	Conf. Neural Information Processing and Intelligent Information
	Systems</em> (ICONIP&apos;98), Japan, October 1998</li>
	<li>
	Rust A G, Adams R, George S &amp;
	Bolouri H, Developmental Evolution of an Edge Detecting Retina,
	Proc. 8th <em>Int. Conf. on Artificial Neural Networks</em>
	(ICANN&apos;98), Sweden, September 1998.</li>
	<li>
	Sabisch T, Ferguson A &amp; Bolouri
	H,  Automatic Registration of Complex Images Using a Self Organizing
	Neural System , Proc. 1998 <em>IEEE International Joint Conference on
	Neural Networks</em> (IJCNN&apos;98), May 4-9 1998, Anchorage, Alaska,
	pp.165-170</li>
	<li>
	Ferguson A, Dixon L C W &amp;
	Bolouri H, Learning Algorithms for RAM-Based Neural Networks, In
	<em>Mathematics of Neural Networks: Models, Algorithms and
	Applications</em>, Eds. Ellacott S W, Mason J C &amp; Anderson I J,
	Kluwer Academic Publishers, pp.181-185, 1997 
	</li>
	<li>
	Peacock C, Bolouri H &amp; Habiger
	C, Multichip Module Manufacture Using Passive Substrate Fault
	Tolerance, IEEE Trans. CPMT , 1997, Vol.20, No.3, pp.320-326 
	</li>
	<li>
	Sabisch T, Ferguson A &amp; Bolouri
	H, Rotation, Translation and Scaling Tolerant Recognition of Complex
	Shapes using a Hierarchical Self-Organising Neural Network, Progress
	in Connectionist-based Information Systems: Proc. of the 1997
	International Conference on <em>Neural Information Processing</em>
	(ICONIP&apos;97), November 24-28 1997, Kasabov, Kozma, Ko, O&apos;shea,
	Coghill, Gedeon (Eds.), Springer, ISBN 981-3083-64-6, pp.1174-1178</li>
	<li>
	Ferguson A &amp; Bolouri H,
	Improving Reinforcement Learning in Stochastic RAM-Based Neural
	Networks, <em>Neural Processing Letters</em>, Kluwer Academic
	Publishers, pp11-15, 1997 
	</li>
	<li>
	Rust A G, Adams R, George S &amp;
	Bolouri H, Activity-Based Pruning in Developmental Artificial Neural
	Networks, Proc. 4th European Conf. on <em>Artificial Life</em>
	(ECAL97), July 1997, Brighton, UK, Eds. Husbands P &amp; Harvey I,
	MIT Press, 224-233</li>
	<li>
	Sabisch T, Ferguson A &amp; Bolouri
	H,  Automatic Landmark Extraction using Self-Organising Maps, Proc.
	<em>IEE/BMVA Int. Conf. on Medical Image Understanding and Analysis</em>,
	7-8 July 1997, University of Oxford, UK, Taylor, C J and Noble, J A
	and Brady J M (Eds.), 157-160</li>
	<li>
	Rust A G, Adams R, George S &amp;
	Bolouri H, Designing Development Rules for Artificial Evolution,
	Proc. 4th Int. Conf. on <em>Artificial Neural Networks and Genetic
	Algorithms</em> (ICANNGA97), University of East Anglia, UK, Smith, G
	D and Steele, N C and Albrecht, R F (Eds.), Springer Verlag,
	508-511, April 1997</li>
	<li>
	Peacock C, Bolouri H &amp; Habiger
	C, Multichip Module Yield Enhancement using Passive Substrate Fault
	Tolerance, Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. on <em>Innovative Systems in
	Silicon</em>, IEEE Computer Society, 198-209, 1996</li>
	<li>
	Ferguson A, Sabisch T, Kaye P H,
	Dixon L C W &amp; Bolouri H, High-Speed Airborne Particle Monitoring
	using Artificial Neural Networks, <em>Advances in Neural Information
	Processing Systems 8</em> (NIPS8), Eds. Touretzky D S, Mozer M C &amp;
	Hasselmo M E, MIT Press, p980-986, 1996 
	</li>
	<li>
	Morgan P, Ferguson A, Dixon L C W &amp;
	Bolouri H, Hardware Implementation of a Real-Valued Sigma-Pi
	Network, Proc. <em>ENNS Int. Conf. on Artificial Neural Networks</em>
	(ICANN&apos;95), 2, 351-356, 1995</li>
	<li>
	Hussaini M B A, Bolouri H &amp; Lea
	R M, Defect and Fault Tolerant Interconnection Strategies for WASP
	Devices, <em>IEEE Trans. CPMT</em>, 18, p406-415, 1995 
	</li>
	<li>
	Peacock C, Bolouri H &amp; Lea R M,
	A Device Life Cycle Analysis of the WSI Associative String
	Processor, <em>IEEE Trans. CPMT</em>, 18, p416-423, 1995 
	</li>
	<li>
	Hussaini M B A, Bolouri H &amp; Lea
	R M, An Evaluation of Defect and Fault Tolerant Signal Routing
	Strategies for WASP Devices, Proc. <em>IEEE Int. Conf. on Wafer Scale
	Integration</em>, 277-287, 1995</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H, Morgan P &amp; Peacock C,
	A RAM-Based Neural Network Architecture for Wafer Scale Integration,
	Proc. <em>IEEE Int. Conf. on Wafer Scale Integration</em>, 82-90, 1995</li>
	<li>
	Peacock C, Bolouri H &amp; Lea R M, 
	A Life-Cycle Model for the WSI Associative String Processor, Proc.
	<em>IEEE Int. Conf. on Wafer Scale Integration</em>, 52-61, 1995</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H, Morgan P &amp; Gurney K,
	Design, Manufacture, and Evaluation of a Probabilistic RAM-Based
	Artificial Neural Network, <em>IEE Electronics Letters</em>, 30(5),
	426-427, March 1994 
	</li>
	<li>
	Hui T, Morgan P, Bolouri H &amp;
	Gurney K, VLSI Implementation of a Probabilistic RAM-Based
	Artificial Neural Network with On-Board Reward-Penalty Learning ,
	<em>VLSI for Neural Networks and Artificial Intelligence</em>, Eds.
	Delgado-Frias J G &amp; Moore W R, Plenum Press, 119-129, 1994 
	</li>
	<li>
	Morgan P, Ferguson A &amp; Bolouri
	H, Cost-Performance Analysis of FPGA, VLSI, and WSI Implementations
	of a RAM-Based Neural Network, Proc. 4th <em>IEEE Int. Conf. On
	Microelectronics for Neural Networks and Fuzzy Systems</em>
	(MicroNeuro&apos;94), 235-243, 1994</li>
	<li>
	Peacock C, Bolouri H &amp; Hedge S
	J, Wafer Scale Integration: the Need for Concurrent Engineering,
	Proc. Int. Conf. on <em>Concurrent Engineering and Electronic Design
	Automation</em> (CEEDA&apos;94), 195-200, 1994</li>
	<li>
	Peacock C &amp; Bolouri H, The
	Effect of Defect Clustering on WASP Device Yields, Proc. <em>IEEE
	Int. Conf. on Wafer Scale Integration</em>, 79-91, 1994</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H, Hussaini M B A &amp; Lea
	R M, Interface Design Optimisation for WASP Devices, Proc. <em>IEEE
	Int. Conf. on Wafer Scale Integration</em>, 223-232, 1993</li>
	<li>
	Sheridan N, Bolouri H &amp; Lea R M,
	The Application of Yield Modelling to the WASP Parallel Processing
	Architecture, Proc. <em>IEEE Int. Conf. on Wafer Scale Integration</em>,
	115-123, 1993</li>
	<li>
	Hui T, Morgan P, Gurney K &amp;
	Bolouri H, A Cascadable 2048-neuron VLSI Artificial Neural Network
	with On-board Learning, <em>Artificial Neural Networks II</em>, Eds.
	Aleksander I &amp; Taylor J, Elsevier Science Publishers, 647-651,
	1992 
	</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H, An Accurate, Virtually
	Cost-Free Yield Model for Defect-Tolerant Large-Area ICs, Proc. Int.
	Conf. on <em>Concurrent Engineering and Electronic Design Automation</em>
	(CEEDA&apos;91), 396-403, 1991</li>
	<li>
	Sheridan N, Bolouri H &amp; Lea R M,
	Architectural Design Optimisation of a Wafer-Scale Massively
	Parallel Processor, Proc. Int. Conf. on <em>Concurrent Engineering
	and Electronic Design Automation</em> (CEEDA&apos;91), 396-403, 1991</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H &amp; Lea R M, Yield
	Considerations in the Design of WASP3, Proc. <em>IEEE Int. Conf. on
	Wafer Scale Integration</em>, 170-177, 1991</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H, The Effect of Modelling
	Tolerances on Yield Estimates of Defect-Tolerant ICs, Proc. <em>IEEE
	Int. Workshop on Defect and Fault Tolerance in VLSI Systems</em>,
	20-33, 1990</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H &amp; Lea R M, Fault
	Tolerance - a Step Towards WSI, <em>IEE Proceedings</em>, Part E,
	135(6), 289-297, November 1988 
	</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H &amp; Lea R M, ULSI and
	WSI Yield Estimation: an Empirical Approach , <em>Yield Modelling and
	Defect Tolerance for VLSI</em>, Eds. Moore W R, Maly W &amp; Strojwas
	A, Adam Hilger, 205-212, 1988 
	</li>
	<li>
	Warren K, Abdelrazik M B A, Bolouri
	H &amp; Lea R M, Power, Clock, and Signal Distribution in the WASP
	Image Processing Device, <em>Wafer Scale Integration II</em>, Eds.
	Saucier G &amp; Trilhe J, Adam Hilger, 1987</li>
	<li>
	Bolouri H &amp; Lea R M, Towards a
	WSI Design Methodology, Proc. <em>Electronic Design Automation
	Conference</em>, 273-278, 1987</li>
</ol>

</p>
</isb:docsubsection>

<isb:docsubsection name="Non-peer-reviewed Articles" label="publications-npr-articles">
<p>
<ol>
	<li>Bolouri
	H, Adams R, George S &amp; Rust A G, Molecular self-organisation in
	a developmental model for the evolution of large-scale Artificial
	Neural Networks, digest of presentations at the workshop on
	appropriate mathematics for evolutionary and developmental biology
	(part of ALife VI), pp.19-21, UCLA, 26 June 1998   
	</li>
	<li>Rubenstein
	&amp; Bolouri H, A Fast Learning, Scalable, Cost-Effective Neural
	Computer, New Electronics, 27(3), 58, March 1994 
	</li>
	<li>Bolouri
	H &amp; Morgan P, A Family of VLSI Neural Processors for Real-Time
	Applications, Digest of the IEE Colloquium on Hardware
	Implementation of Neural Networks and Fuzzy Logic, 4/1-4/2, March
	1994</li>
	<li>Ferguson
	A, Morgan P, Bolouri H &amp; Gurney K, Learning and Topology
	Optimisation in Large Scale HyperNets, Proc. Int. Workshop on
	Weightless Neural Networks 150-155, April 1993 
	</li>
	<li>Peacock
	C &amp; Bolouri H, A Neural Network Controlled Mobile Robot, Proc.
	Inst. Measurement &amp; Control Colloq. on Neural Networks and Fuzzy
	Logic in Measurement and Control, 1993 
	</li>
	<li>Bolouri
	H,  Automated Fabrication Yield Optimisation as Part of Concurrent
	Engineering in the Design of Ultra Large Scale and Wafer Scale
	Integrated Circuits, Proc. Sunderland Advanced Manufacturing
	Technology Conference, April 1992 
	</li>
	<li>Hui
	T, Wilkes, Morgan P, Bolouri H &amp; Gurney K, The Design of a
	VLSI-Based Artificial Neural Network by a Student Group, Digest of
	the IEE Colloquium on The Eurochip Project: VLSI Design in
	Education, 6/1-6/3, 1993 
	</li>
	<li>McKirdy,
	Abdelrazik, Bolouri, Hedge, Warren &amp; Lea, Comparative Appraisal
	of the Implementation of an Image Processing Module using WSI and
	VLSI ASPs, Digest of the IEE Colloquium on The Eurochip Project:
	VLSI Design in Education, 1986</li>
</ol>
</p>
</isb:docsubsection>

<isb:docsubsection name="Editorials and Reviews" label="publications-editorials">
<p>
<ol>
	<li>Bolouri
	H., La Forge L., Foreword to Special Section on Systems In Silicon,
	IEEE Transactions on CPMT, vol.21, no.4, p.322.</li>
	<li>
	Compton A, Bolouri H &amp; Nathan A,
	Arrythmia Recognition Strategies and Hardware Decisions for the
	Implantable Cardioverter-Defibrillator - a Review, <em>Med. Eng.
	Phys.</em>, 17(2), p96-103, 1995 
	</li>
</ol>
</p>
</isb:docsubsection>

<isb:docsubsection name="Book Chapters, Monographs" label="publications-bookchapters">
<p>
<ol>
        <li>Rust A G, Adams R, Schilstra M and Bolouri H,
        Evolving Computational Neural Systems Using Synthetic Developmental
        Mechanisms,  <em>On Growth, Form and Computers,</em>
        Kumar S and Bentley, P J (eds), Academic Press, London, UK
        (in press)</li>
	<li>Bolouri
	H, and Schilstra M.J., Models of genetic regulatory networks, in
	Computation in Cells, Eds Paton, Holcombe, Parish &amp; Bolouri,
	Springer, to appear in 2002.</li>
        <li>
        Rust A G, Adams R, George S and Bolouri H, Towards Computational Neural 
        Systems Through Developmental Evolution, <em>Emergent Neural Computation 
        Architectures based on Neuroscience</em>,Wermter S, Austin J and Willshaw D J 
        (eds), Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence (LNAI2036), 188-202, 
        Springer-Verlag, 2001</li>
	<li>Yuh
	C-H, Bolouri H, Davidson E.H., A logical model of Cis-regulatory
	control in a eukaryotic system, in Computational modelling of
	genetic and biochemical systems, Eds. Bower &amp; Bolouri, MIT
	Press, 2001, pp.73-100.</li>
</ol>
</p>
</isb:docsubsection>

<isb:docsubsection name="Books" label="publications-books">
<p>
<ol>
	<li>
	Bower, James and Bolouri, Hamid
	(Eds.), Computational Modeling of Genetic and Biochemical Networks,
	MIT Press, Feb 2001</li>
	<li>
	LaForge, Bolouri, Sciuto, &amp;
	Tewksbury (Eds.), Proceedings of the 2nd IEEE International
	Conference on Innovative Systems In Silicon (ISIS&apos;97), Austin,
	Texas, October 8-10 1997</li>
</ol>
</p>
</isb:docsubsection>

</isb:docsection>


<hr />

<p>
This page was last updated on: <code>2003/04/09</code><br />
For corrections, please e-mail: <code>&mainEmailSafe;</code>.
</p>


</isb:document>
