<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="../config/documentation-stylesheet.xml"?>
<!DOCTYPE isbdocument [
  <!ENTITY % AppConfig SYSTEM "../config/AppConfig.dtd">
  %AppConfig;
   ]>

<isb:document xmlns:isb="http://www.systemsbiology.org/xmlns"
              xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1"
              xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1">

<isb:doctitle>&appName; User Manual</isb:doctitle>
<isb:docowner>&appMaintainerFullName;, &appMaintainerAffiliation;</isb:docowner>
<isb:docownerurl>&appMaintainerURL;</isb:docownerurl>
<isb:docdate>$Date$</isb:docdate>
<isb:docowneremail>&appMaintainerEmailSafe;</isb:docowneremail>

<isb:doccontents />

<isb:docsection name="Introduction" label="introduction">
<p>
The &appName; project is a library (collection) of classes
written in the <a href="http://java.sun.com">Java</a>
programming language, that are intended to be used for
research in computational biology.  
</p>
<p>
This document is the user manual for the &appName; library.
This manual applies to the following release version of the library:
<blockquote>
<pre>
release version:   &appVersion;
release date:      &appDate;
</pre>
</blockquote>
The release notes for this version of the library can be found
at the following URL:
<blockquote>
<a href="ReadMe.html">&appHomePage;/docs/ReadMe.html</a>
</blockquote>
The home page for this library is:
<blockquote>
<a href="&appHomePage;">&appHomePage;</a>
</blockquote>
The version history for this library can be found at the following URL:
<blockquote>
<a href="VersionHistory.html">&appHomePage;/docs/VersionHistory.html</a>
</blockquote>
If you are reading this document through a print-out, you can find
the online version of this document (which may be a more recent version)
at the following URL:
<blockquote>
<a href="UserManual.html">&appHomePage;/docs/UserManual.html</a>
</blockquote>
</p>

</isb:docsection>

<isb:docsection name="Requirements" label="requirements">
You will need the Sun Java Development Kit (JDK) vesrion 1.4 
or newer (or the equivalent) in order to use these classes.
Some of the packages in this source directory tree
require external Java packages/libraries to be installed.
In particular, in order to be able to compile the full
source tree, you will need to have the following Java libraries
installed and available within your <code>CLASSPATH</code> environment
variable:
<blockquote>
<table border="1">
<tr>
<td>Package name</td><td>JAR name</td><td>Source</td><td>License</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>jfreechart</td><td><code>jfreechart-&lt;VERS&gt;.jar</code></td>
<td><a href="http://www.jfree.org/jfreechart"><code>www.jfree.org/jfreechart/</code></a></td><td>LGPL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>jcommon</td><td><code>jcommon-&lt;VERS&gt;.jar</code></td>
<td><a href="http://www.jfree.org/jcommon"><code>www.jfree.org/jcommon/</code></a></td><td>LGPL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SBW (core)</td><td><code>SBWCore.jar</code></td>
<td><a href="http://www.sbw-sbml.org/sbw/software"><code>www.sbw-sbml.org/sbw/software/</code></a></td><td>LGPL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SBML Validator</td><td><code>SBMLValidate.jar</code></td>
<td><a href="http://www.sbw-sbml.org/sbw/software"><code>www.sbw-sbml.org/sbw/software/</code></a></td><td>LGPL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>JavaHelp</td><td><code>jh.jar</code></td>
<td><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javahelp"><code>java.sun.com/products/javahelp</code></a></td><td>Sun Binary Code License</td>
</tr>
</table>
</blockquote>
Note that the SBW/SBML libraries and packages are only required for
compiling the code in the &quot;<code>org.systemsbiology.chem.sbw</code>&quot; 
directory.  By omitting this
directory from the compilation (by adding a suitable 
&quot;<code>exclude</code>&quot; to the
&quot;<code>javac</code>&quot; statements in the 
<code>build.xml</code> file), in principle the resulting
<code>&localJavaLibraryName;.jar</code> file that would be built, 
would not have any dependencies on 
the aforementioned SBW/SBML libraries.  
<p />
The <code>jfreechart</code> and <code>jcommon</code> libraries
are needed in order to compile the <code>org.systemsbiology.chem.app</code>
package.  They are not needed for any other packages in the &appName;
library.
<p />
The classes in this library
have been tested on the Sun JDK v1.4.1, on the Red Hat
Linux 8.0 platform and on Windows XP.  On other platforms,
your mileage may vary.
<p />
Ant is required to use the "build.xml" file in this directory.
You can download and install Ant from 
<a href="http://ant.apache.org">the apache Ant project</a>.
</isb:docsection>

<isb:docsection name="Naming Conventions" label="namingconventions">
<p />
A few notes about conventions used these java packages.
The &quot;.tp&quot; suffix at the end of a package name
indicates that the &quot;.tp&quot; 
subpackage contains test programs for
the parent package.  Similarly, a suffix &quot;.t&quot;
at the end of a package name indicates that the 
&quot;.t&quot; subpackage contains unit tests for the
parent package (in the JUnit framework).  
<p />
These classes are all in development, and are subject
to change at any time, without notice.  All classes contained
herein should be considered copyright of the &mainAffiliation;, 
2003.  
</isb:docsection>

<isb:docsection name="Using the library" label="using">
<p>
In order to use this library, you will need to download and
run the installer available on the 
<a href="&webBaseURL;/&localJavaLibraryName;">&localJavaLibraryName;
home page</a>.  When you run the installer, you will be prompted
to specify an installation directory.
</p>
<p>
The documentation will
be stored in a subdirectory &quot;<code>docs</code>&quot;
of the installation directory.  Note that the Javadoc documentation 
is not provided by the installer, but you can generate it using
the &quot;<code>javadoc</code>&quot; program available from the
Sun Java Development Kit (JDK).  You can also 
<a href="&webBaseURL;/&localJavaLibraryName;/javadoc">browse
the Javadoc API for &localJavaLibraryName;</a> on the web.
</p>
<p>
The compiled Java code for the library is contained in the
file &quot;<code>&localJavaLibraryName;.jar</code>&quot;, which is stored in the
&quot;<code>lib</code>&quot; subdirectory of the installation
directory.  In order to be able to use this library in your
Java programs, you will need to ensure that the aforementioned
JAR file (<code>&localJavaLibraryName;.jar</code>) is added to your Java
<code>CLASSPATH</code>.  This can be done by modifying (or
defining) the <code>CLASSPATH</code> environment variable,
or it can be done by passing the &quot;<code>-cp</code>&quot;
argument to the &quot;<code>javac</code>&quot; and 
&quot;<code>java</code>&quot; commands when compiling and
running your program, respectively.
</p>

</isb:docsection>

<isb:docsection name="API Documentation" label="apidocumentation">
<p>
For technical reasons, the API documentation has been
separated from the User Manual for the &localJavaLibraryName; library.
The API documentation is available on-line at:
<blockquote>
<a href="&webBaseURL;/&localJavaLibraryName;/javadoc">&webBaseURL;/&localJavaLibraryName;/javadoc</a>
</blockquote>
There is also a PDF version available at:
<blockquote>
<a href="&webBaseURL;/&localJavaLibraryName;/docs/APIDocumentation.pdf">&webBaseURL;/&localJavaLibraryName;/docs/APIDocumentation.pdf</a>
</blockquote>
Please note that the PDF documentation is generated using
an experimental Javadoc-to-PDF translater, so there are
some glitches in the formatting of the PDF.  At this time,
the HTML Javadoc is the more readable format and has the more
comprehensive network of hyperlinks.
</p>

</isb:docsection>

<isb:docsection name="Source Code" label="sourcecode">
<p>
The source code for the &localJavaLibraryName; library 
is included with the library installer.  You can find the code 
in the file &quot;<code>&localJavaLibraryName;-src.tar.gz</code>&quot;
that is installed in the &quot;<code>src</code>&quot;
subdirectory of the installation directory for this program.
</p>
</isb:docsection>

<isb:docsection name="Getting Help" label="gettinghelp">
<p>
If you find that the &appName; library does not function in accordance
with the descriptions in this manual, or if there are sections of
this manual that are incorrect or unclear, the authors would like to 
hear about it, so that we can make improvements and fix bugs in the
software.  Furthermore, the authors would appreciate feedback
regarding new features or improvements that would be useful to
users of this software.  Before e-mailing the authors, it is a good
idea to check the <a href="&appHomePage;">&appName; application home page</a>
to see if a new version has been released, in which your specific
problem may have been corrected.  All releases are documented in
the &quot;version history&quot; page accessible from the home page.
The best way to contact the authors is to send e-mail to:
<blockquote>
<code>&appMaintainerEmailSafe;</code>.
</blockquote>
The authors will attempt to respond to your e-mail as quickly as
possible.
</p>
<p>
If you are reporting a bug, or something that you suspect is a bug,
please provide as much information as you can about your specific
installation of the &appName; library.  In particular, please provide
us with the version number of the &appName; library that you are using,
the type and version number of the Java Runtime Environment that you
are using (e.g., Sun JRE version 1.4.1), and your operating system
type and verion (e.g., Red Hat Linux 8.0).  Furthermore, if the
problem is with a specific Java program using the library, please send
us the source code of the complete program that generates the problem.
Note that some effort to localize the problem to a reproducible
test case with a small program, will help us significantly in fixing
the problem that you are encountering.  If the problem that you 
encountered generated a &quot;stack backtrace&quot; on the console,
please include the full stack backtrace text in your bug report.
Please also send us the text of any error message that you may 
have been reported by the library, in a dialog box or on the console.
Providing this information will dramatically increase the likelihood
that the authors will be able to quickly and successfully resolve
the problem that you are encountering. 
</p>

</isb:docsection>

</isb:document>
