<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="../../../config/documentation-stylesheet.xml"?>
<!DOCTYPE isbdocument [
  <!ENTITY % AppConfig SYSTEM "../config/AppConfig.dtd">
  %AppConfig;
   ]>

<!--
  Copyright (C) 2003 by Institute for Systems Biology,
  Seattle, Washington, USA.  All rights reserved.
  
  This document is distributed under the GNU Lesser 
  General Public License, the text of which is available at:
    http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html
 -->

<!-- ========== PREAMBLE ========== -->

<isb:document xmlns:isb="http://www.systemsbiology.org/xmlns"
              xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1"
              xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1">

<isb:doctitle>&appName; Version History</isb:doctitle>
<isb:docowner>&appMaintainerFullName;, &appMaintainerAffiliation;</isb:docowner>
<isb:docownerurl>&appMaintainerURL;</isb:docownerurl>
<isb:docdate>$Date$</isb:docdate>
<isb:docowneremail>&appMaintainerEmailSafe;</isb:docowneremail>

<p>
This document contains the version history for the
<a href="../">&appName;</a> software product.
</p>

<p>
<table border="1">
<tr valign="top">
<td>Version</td>
<td>Date</td>
<td>Comments</td>
<td>Built with 
<a href="&webBaseURL;/&localJavaLibraryName;">&localJavaLibraryName;</a> version number:</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>1.1.2</td>
<td>2004/01/13</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>An operating system-specific installer is now available for the Mac OSX platform.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the layout of the simulation launcher control screen, where the 
full text of the &quot;select all&quot; button was not being displayed.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the simulation launcher 
where the simulation was not being cancelled, in the case where the user
selects too many symbols for displaying on a plot.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the chemical model definition language (CMDL) parser where the
application was aborting when the parser encountered a mathematical expression that 
has invalid syntax.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the chemical model definition language (CMDL) parser
where parsing errors in the model definition file were resulting in the exception class
name being unnecessarily included in the message part of the exception.</li>
<li>Changed the simulation results plotter so that the
vertical axis label is the more generally applicable &quot;value&quot; rather than 
&quot;populations&quot;.</li>
<li>Added a new Systems Biology Workbench (SBW) simulation service, for the 
Gibson-Bruck stochastic simulation algorithm.</li>
<li>Modified the &quot;Register SBW Simulators&quot; program so that it
registers services for all three supported simulators:  Gibson-Bruck, Gillespie,
and Deterministic.</li>
<li>Implemented a work-around for an InstallAnywhere bug, so that the &appName;
program now launches correctly when installed on a Mac OSX computer.</li>
<li>The InstallAnywhere installer for &appName; now logs error messages to a log file
&quot;<code>ins&appName;.log</code>&quot;.</li>
</ul>
</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>1.1.1</td>
<td>2004/01/05</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Modified the delayed reaction solver so that the internal running
window average is recalculated from scratch, each time a minimum
number of points (default 4000) has been inserted into the queue.
</li>
<li>Fixed a file-loading bug pertaining to the case where the model 
builder fails to construct the model from the model definition file.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher to dump a stack backtrace to the 
terminal window if a low-level error condition is detected.</li>
<li>Generalized the multi-step reaction solver into a &quot;delayed&quot;
reaction solver, to permit phenomenological
modelling of reaction processes with an intrinsic time delay.</li>
<li>Changed the command language model builder to add language extensions
for specifying a multistep or delayed reaction.</li>
<li>Fixed bugs in the main editor window and the plot window,
where window resizing was not working correctly on the Windows platform.</li>
<li>Removed unnecessary label from main editor window, which was taking up 
space on the screen.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td>
1.1.1
</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>1.1.0</td>
<td>2003/12/22</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Added a <code>reload</code> menu item, which is used for reloading the model
that is currently in the editor window, into the simulation launcher.  It replaces
the model that is currently loaded into the simulation launcher.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the simulation launcher, where it would still display a graph
even when the simulation was cancelled.</li>
<li>Made the simulation plot window dynamically resizable.</li>
<li>Made the main editor window dynamically resizable.</li>
<li>Added a hook to the simulation launcher so that an external application can 
dynamically replace the model loaded in the simulation launcher.</li>
<li>Added a hook to the simulation launcher so that an external application can
detect when a simulation starts or ends.</li>
<li>Fixed bug where the &appName; command language interpreter was
rejecting model definition files that ended with whitespace.</li>
<li>Added an &quot;append&quot; check-box to the simulation launcher
window, which allows for specifying that the output file should be appended to, rather than overwritten.</li>
<li>Added a &quot;save as PNG image&quot; button to the simulation results plot 
window, which is used to save the plot as a PNG image file.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher to display all symbols (not just species) 
in the list-box of symbols that can be displayed in the simulation results.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher to allow for an external application to
hide the Output Type controls, and added a callback mechanism to return the simulation
results to the calling application using a queue data structure.</li>
<li>Added support for copying the simulation results plot image to the 
system clipboard, on operating systems that support image transfer to the
clipboard (e.g., Windows).</li>
<li>Added full-text search capability for the online application help.</li>
<li>The application help frame is now initially centered in the screen.</li>
<li>Added a &quot;select all symbols&quot; feature to the simulation launcher.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td>
1.1.0
</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>1.0.0</td>
<td>2003/12/08</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Added new deterministic (ODE) simulators &appName;,
based on the &quot;odeToJava&quot; library for numerical solution of ODEs.  This library
includes a Dortmand-Prince 4/5 Runge-Kuta solver with adaptive step-size control, and
an implicit/explicit Runge-Kutta solver with adaptive step-size control (for models
with a high degree of stiffness).</li>
<li>Modified the SBML reader to permit inclusion of &quot;rules&quot; in SBML models</li>
<li>Modified the SBML writer to export models in SBML level 1, version 2.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in which the operation does not terminate, when model-building
fails after the user selects &quot;Export&quot; from the &quot;Tools&quot; menu.</li>
<li>Created separate fields in the SimulationLauncher
for specifying the matximum allowed relative and absolute errors</li>
<li>Fixed a bug for the case of a parameter defined as a deferred-evaluation
expression</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td>
1.0.0
</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.8</td>
<td>2003/11/21</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Modified the fixed-stepsize deterministic simulator so that it can detect when the
simulation error exceeds a certain threshold, and produce a human-comprehensible 
error message (the message suggests that the step-size be decreased).</li>
<li>Modified the &quot;simulation launcher&quot; pane so that it has text-box controls
for specifying separate simulator-specific parameters, such as the ensemble size, the
minimum number of steps, and the maximum allowed fractional error.  Default values
are auto-filled in these new fields, depending on the type of simulator selected.  The
&quot;ensemble size&quot; and &quot;number of steps&quot; are now separate fields.</li>
<li>The &quot;plot&quot; output type no longer gives a strange error message when
a &quot;NaN&quot; (not-a-number) appears in the simulation output.  It now gives a more
human-comprehensible error message.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td>0.0.8</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.7</td>
<td>2003/11/07</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Modified the editor pane so that it &quot;remembers&quot; the directory of the last file
that was opened; the default directory for the file chooser for the next &quot;open&quot; command,
is set to this directory.</li>
<li>Fixed a problem where the ISB and Bolouri Lab logo images were not displaying in the on-line
help screen, when the computer is not connected to the network.</li>
<li>Removed the table of contents from the HTML User Manual used in the on-line help (the JavaHelp
environment provides its own table of contents).</li>
<li>Adjusted the default vertical dimension of the editor pane for the model editor, to 40 characters.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td>0.0.7</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.6</td>
<td>2003/10/22</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>In the &appName; simulation launcher form, made &quot;Plot&quot; the default output mode</li>
<li>Redefined how the stochastic simulators compute
reaction rates for dimerization reactions, for model interchangability with the ODE simulators.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td>0.0.6</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.5</td>
<td>2003/10/20</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed a bug in the Gibson-Bruck simulator, for the case of a boundary
reactant species.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the command-language parser, it can
now accept tabs as valid whitespace in the model definition file.</li>  
<li>The
SBML import feature can now process model definition files that conform to the
SBML Level 1, Version 2 specification.</li>  
<li>Fixed a bug in which &appName; would
fail to start, in the case where &appName; was installed in the top-level
directory of a Windows (or DOS) drive.</li> 
<li>Redefined how the stochastic simulators compute
reaction rates for dimerization reactions, for model interchangability with the ODE simulators.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td>0.0.5</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.4</td>
<td>2003/08/28</td>
<td>Modified the Cytoscape bridge to use JNLP, so Cytoscape does not have to be bundled with Dizzy</td>
<td>0.0.4</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.3</td>
<td>2003/08/26</td>
<td>Added the ability to simulate a multistep chemical reaction as a single composite reaction</td>
<td>0.0.3</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.2</td>
<td>2003/08/06</td>
<td>Added the ability to display a model in a <a href="&cytoscapeURL;">Cytoscape</a> window.</td>
<td>0.0.2</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.1</td>
<td>2003/08/04</td>
<td>First version of the program.  It is an alpha version,
intended only for internal use at &mainAffiliation;.</td>
<td>0.0.1</td>
</tr>

</table>
</p>

</isb:document>
