<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="../../../config/documentation-stylesheet.xml"?>
<!DOCTYPE isbdocument [
  <!ENTITY % AppConfig SYSTEM "../config/AppConfig.dtd">
  %AppConfig;

<!ENTITY javaURL "&webBaseURL;/&localJavaLibraryName;">
   ]>

<!--
  Copyright (C) 2003 by Institute for Systems Biology,
  Seattle, Washington, USA.  All rights reserved.
  
  This document is distributed under the GNU Lesser 
  General Public License, the text of which is available at:
    http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html
 -->

<!-- ========== PREAMBLE ========== -->

<isb:document xmlns:isb="http://www.systemsbiology.org/xmlns"
              xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1"
              xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1">

<isb:doctitle>&appName; Version History</isb:doctitle>
<isb:docowner>&appMaintainerFullName;, &appMaintainerAffiliation;</isb:docowner>
<isb:docownerurl>&appMaintainerURL;</isb:docownerurl>
<isb:docdate>$Date$</isb:docdate>
<isb:docowneremail>&appMaintainerEmailSafe;</isb:docowneremail>

<p>
This document contains the version history for the
<a href="../">&appName;</a> software product.
</p>

<p>
<table border="1">
<tr valign="top">
<td>Version</td>
<td>Date</td>
<td>Comments</td>
<td>Built with 
<a href="&javaURL;">&localJavaLibraryName;</a> version number:</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.11.2/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.11.2</a></td>
<td>2006/01/26</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>
Included the latest version of the Systems Biology Workbench (SBW) library,
which will allow &appName; to interoperate with SBW version 2.5.0.
</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/2.4.1/download.html">2.4.1</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.11.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.11.1</a></td>
<td>2005/08/11</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>
Fixed a bug in the editor pane, where a
<code>NullPointerException</code> was occurring when the user
attempted to run "Tools-&gt;Simulate" on a model that did not have a
filename associated with it yet.
</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/2.4.1/download.html">2.4.1</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.11.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.11.0</a></td>
<td>2005/07/08</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>
  Added a "command-language" model exporter, which will export
  the model to Chemical Model Definition Language (CMDL) Format.
</li>
<li>
  Fixed a bug where the file browser for "export model" was not
  set to the current working directory.  Exporting a model also
  now resets the current working directory, for consistency with
  other file operations in the application.
</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/2.4.0/download.html">2.4.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.10.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.10.0</a></td>
<td>2005/07/01</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Modified the Systems Biology Workbench (SBW) interface so
  that the &appName; simulation launcher is now an "Analysis
  Service".  This means that the &appName; simulation service
  shows up in the "SBW" menu in JDesigner and other SBW-enabled
  tools.</li>
<li>The "About &appName;" menu item now displays the copyright
  notice.</li>
<li>Updated the version of the external SBW library 
  (<core>SBWCore.jar</core>) to version 2.3.0.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/2.3.0/download.html">2.3.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.9.3/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.9.3</a></td>
<td>2005/06/19</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Added a work-around for a bug in the Systems Biology Workbench
(SBW) interface, that could potentially cause the simulation service
to fail to register with the SBW Broker on non-Windows systems.
Thanks to Frank Bergmann for supplying the patch.</li>
<li>Added a new method to the SBW interface, that allows a
CMDL model to be passed to &appName; via SBW.  Using this
feature requires knowing how to programmatically call the SBW.
File inclusion via the <code>#include</code> directive is not
allowed, when passing model text to &appName; via the SBW interface
(for security reasons).</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/2.2.2/download.html">2.2.2</a></td>
</tr>

  
<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.9.2/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.9.2</a></td>
<td>2005/06/15</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed problem with build script, where it was impossible to do any
ant tasks, even those tasks that do not require InstallAnywhere,
on a system that does not have the InstallAnywhere JAR file installed
into the Ant lib directory.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug where the "File->Close" menu item was not being enabled 
after the user loads a zero-length file into the edit buffer.</li>
<li>Fixing missing sample file "Michaelis.cmdl".  Removed unneeded
sample file "sample-model-sbml.xml".</li>
<li>Fixed a problem where the <code>RegisterSBWSimulators</code> launcher
was failing with an exception, when the installed version of the 
Systems Biology Workbench (SBW) is 2.0.0 or greater.  Now, &appName;
works correctly with SBW version 2.2.1 or newer.  This has the side effect
that the version of &appName; distributed through the graphical installer
will not work with 1.X.X versions of the SBW.  However, see the
<a href="UserManual.html#sbwinterface">user manual</a> for information
about how to make &appName; compatible with 1.X.X versions of SBW.  Thanks
to Stanley Ng and Ole Schulz-Trieglaf for reporting this problem.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/2.2.1/download.html">2.2.1</a></td>
</tr>


<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.9.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.9.1</a></td>
<td>2005/04/05</td>
<td>
<ul>
  <li>
  Fixed a <code>NullPointerException</code> that was occurring when a model contained
  a species whose initial population value exceeded the maximum allowed for stochastic
  simulations.  This exception would occur the <em>second</em> time the user attempted
  to initiate a stochastic simulation.  The correct behavior is for the simulator to
  give the same error message each time the user attempts to run a stochastic simulation
  with the (flawed) model. Thanks to Vincent Rouilly for submitting the bug report.</li>
  <li>
  Improved the error message shown by the simulation launcher, when the user attempts to
  launch a stochastic simulation and when one of the species has an initial population value that exceeds the maximum 
  allowed for stochastic simulations.  The error message now gives the offending species name and
  the initial population value.
  </li>
  <li>
  Fixed a bug whereby a SBML model with <code>UTF-8</code> character encoding (and actually using special
  UTF-8 characters) loaded into
  the editor pane, and then subsequently passed to the "simulate..." or the "export model" menu
  item, would 
  cause a <code>SAXParserException</code> on the Macintosh OSX platform.  Thanks to Vincent Rouilly
  for submitting this bug report.</li>  
  <li>
  Fixed a bug in the simulation launcher where the
  "secs remaining" text field would show too many significant digits when the number
  of estimated seconds remaining is very large.
  </li>
    <li>
  Fixed a potential problem with the editor pane, such that when the user selected
  "save as" or "save", the file was being written with the platform's default character encoding.  This
  meant that (in the case of SBML models) the encoding specified in the XML header was
  being ignored, and (in the case of CMDL models) the model would not be written in
  the UTF-8 encoding on platforms whose default encoding is not UTF-8.  This means that
  on certain platforms, the "save" or "save as" functions would end up writing
  a file that does not conform to published character encoding specifications for SBML and CMDL.      
  </li>
  <li>
  Fixed a bug in in the "View..." -&gt; "human-readable" menu item feature, 
  where the comma-and-newline 
  separator string was not being printed in every case that it should have.  This
  led to improperly formatted output for the "human-readable" view/export feature.
  </li>
  <li>Fixed a bug in the simulation engine that was
    causing incorrect results when simulating certain SBML 
    models that have "substance" units of "mole".   Thanks to Vincent Rouilly for 
    submitting the bug report.  This bug does not affect the results of
    SBML models with "substance" units of "item" or CMDL models.</li> 
 <li>Fixed a bug in the editor pane that was causing
    the editor to fail to "forget" the model parser type,
    when the edit buffer is cleared using the "File" -&gt; "Close" menu item.</li>
  <li>Modified the stochastic simulators to check all
    dynamical symbols to see if any species value exceeds the maximum allowed for stochastic
    simulations (approximately 9.0771993e+15), each time a "result time point" is sampled
    (by default, 100 time points spaced at equal intervals during the simulation).
    This ensures that the stochastic simulators will continuously check to
    see if any species values exceed the maximum allowed species value, throughout the
    course of the simulation.  This fixes a potential problem with a simulation
    such as
    <blockquote>
      <pre>
X = 1.0e+15;
-&gt; X, 1.0;
      </pre>
    </blockquote>
    which will eventually fail in a stochastic simulator, due numeric precision
    limitations of floating-point addition.
    </li>    
    <li>Improved the wording of some error messages in the simulation launcher window,
      the editor pane, and for various menu functions.</li>
  <li>Fixed bug in the <code>runmodel</code> program 
    where the command-line simulation launcher was not obtaining the defualt 
relative and absolute error tolerances for the simulator, so the user would get an error
if both tolerances were not explicitly specified on the command-line.</li>      
  <li>Modified the "Tools -&gt; View... &gt; cytoscape" feature so that
     the <code>NetX</code> start-up dialog box does not appear at application start-up.
     The dialog box asks you where you want to store your NetX cache.  After this 
     modification, the dialog box should only appear the first time you actually use 
     this feature.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/2.2.0/download.html">2.2.0</a></td>
</tr>


<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.9.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.9.0</a></td>
<td>2005/02/04</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>
  Added a new section &quot;<a href="UserManual.html#simulators">Simulators</a>&quot; to the
  User Manual, describing the different simulators that are available in &appName;
</li>
<li>
  Fixed a potential problem with the sample programs for creating &appName; models using
  the &localJavaLibraryName; API, where the reserved symbol mapper was not being set for the
  model.  This was leading to confusion when people attempted to reference reserved symbols
  in expressions, which was causing an exception to be thrown.  This is just a documentation
  change.
</li>
<li>
  Fixed a <code>NullPointerException</code> that occurs when the model editor buffer
  has no filename defined for it (i.e., when the buffer has not yet been saved to a file), and
  when there is a parser error in processing the model definition text.  Improved some
  parser error messages to make them more human-comprehensible.
</li>
<li>
  Fixed a bug in the editor code where the "save as" operation was failing to update the
  "current directory" that is used for preprocessor file inclusion.
</li>
<li>
  Fixed a bug in the CMDL parser which was causing an exception to be thrown, when a 
  model contained a loop definition in which either the start or stop value was a 
  mathematical expression containing parentheses.
</li>
<li>
  Added support for a <code>min()</code> and <code>max()</code> function, to the
  mathematical expression-processing engine.  Mathematical expressions in the CMDL
  can now use these two functions, as functions of two arguments, such as
  <blockquote>
    <code>min(A,B)</code>
  </blockquote>
  Thanks to Adam Duguid, for submitting the source code patch.
</li>
<li>
  Fixed confusing error messages in the Runge-Kutta simulator with fixed step-size,
  for the case when the relative error tolerance is exceeded.
</li>
<li>
  Modified the simulation launcher screen and the command-line simulation launcher program
  to permit disabling the error checking in the fixed-stepsize Runge-Kutta simulator
  (<code>ODE-RK5-fixed</code>).  In the simulation launcher screen, the error checking
  is disabled by deleting the relative and/or absolute error tolerance parameters in the 
  corresponding text entry boxes.  In the simulation launcher command-line program,
  the error checking is disabled by passing an argument modifier "null" after the
  corresponding command-line argument, such as 
  <blockquote>
    <pre>-relativeTolerance null</pre>
  </blockquote>
  Each of the error types can be disabled separately, or they can be disabled together.
</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/2.1.0/download.html">2.1.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.8.2/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.8.2</a></td>
<td>2004/11/18</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>
  Decreased the application start-up time by 45%, by making
  the search for plug-in components more efficient.
</li>
<li>
  Created a "View" sub-menu of "Tools", containing the aliases
  of all <a href="UserManual.html#viewhuman">model viewers</a>.
  Moved the "View in Cytoscape" and "View in Human-Readable
  Format" menu items to this new sub-menu.
</li>
<li>
  Created a "Export" sub-menu of "Tools", containing the aliases
  of all the <a href="UserManual.html#exporterplugins">model
  exporters</a>.  The aliases that used to appear in a dialog
  box when the "Export..." menu item was selected, now appear
  in the "Export" sub-menu.
</li>
<li>
  Added a "line counter" feature to the main model editor window.
  The line number of the current cursor position in the editor buffer
  is displayed, and updated whenever you move the cursor in the editor
  window.  Thanks to Earl Solis, for suggesting this useful feature.
</li>
<li>
  Added new sample model definition file, <code>Michaelis.cmdl</code>, 
  to the &quot;<code>samples</code>&quot; directory.
</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/2.0.1/download.html">2.0.1</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.8.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.8.1</a></td>
<td>2004/11/12</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>
  Please note that there have been some changes in the
  &localJavaLibraryName; API in this release.  For more
  information, please refer to the description of changes in 
  version 2.0.0 in the 
  <a href="&javaURL;/docs/VersionHistory.html">&localJavaLibraryName; Version History</a>.
</li>
<li>
Fixed a bug in the simulation results table window,
which was causing the table window to not be resizable.
</li>
<li>
Modified the simulation engine to better handle formatting
of not-a-number (<code>NaN</code>) and infinity values, in
simulation results.
</li>
<li>
Modified the <code>runmodel</code> program so that it will
notify the user if the simulator is not capable of computing
steady-state fluctuations, if the 
<code>-computeFluctuations</code> flag is passed on the
command-line.
</li>
<li>
Fixed a bug in the CMDL parser which caused an exception
when one attempts to simulate a model containing a macro
reference embedded within another macro definition.
</li>
<li>
Fixed a bug in the editor pane.  When the user would close
the file loaded in the editor pane and then attempt to open
a new file, the user would be needlessly prompted as to whether
to save the changes in the editor buffer, to a file.  
</li>
<li>
Modified the CMDL to enable the parsing of floating-point
numeric literals expressed in scientific notation, such as
<code>1.0e-7</code> and <code>2.7e+14</code>.
</li>
<li>
Fixed a bug where ISO-8859-1 characters greater than 127 in the CMDL 
model definition file were causing exceptions when the model was 
processed, on Red Hat Linux.  CMDL files are now always processed using
UTF-8 encoding.  This will ensure that CMDL model processing
is consistent across different locales.  Files opened using the "include" 
directive will be processed in the same character set as the parent file.
</li>
<li>
Fixed a potential bug 
where SBML files were being read in the default
locale encoding for text files, and not in the encoding specified in the
XML file header.
</li>
<li>
Fixed a bug (reported by Alex Kowald) in the 
<code>org.systemsbiology.chem.ModelBuilderCommandLanguage</code>
in which an exception is thrown, if a
quoted string is embedded within a deferred-evaluation mathematical
expression.  This prevents referencing a symbol name that contains
an integer (e.g., an index) obtained from a mathematical expression,
within the context of a deferred-evaluation mathematical expression.
This bug potentially affects models in which the loop construct is used,
in conjunction with reaction definitions with complex (deferred-evaluation)
kinetic rate expressions.
</li>
<li>
Slight change to the help browser, so that it will not take up
all the screen, when the screen size is very large.  The 
initial size of the help browser window is now capped at 
800x600 (but can be modified by the user), and will never
exceed 80% of the screen size in either dimension.
</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/2.0.0/download.html">2.0.0</a></td>
</tr>


<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.8.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.8.0</a></td>
<td>2004/10/11</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>
Fixed a bug in the build file that was preventing the source code from
being included in the <code>&localJavaLibraryName;</code> source distribution archives.
</li>
<li>
Modified the chemical model definition language to disallow user definition
of a symbol that begins with an underscore character.  This ensures that
user-defined symbols will not conflict with the names of automatically
defined symbols (such as automatically defined chemical reaction names).
</li>
<li>
Modified the simulation launcher window so that internal
symbols are never displayed in the listbox of symbols,
and in the text output of the command-line simulation launcher.
</li>
<li>
Fixed a bug in the <code>repressilator.xml</code> sample file; the
<code>listOfUnitDefinitions</code> section was omitted, which was
causing the initial species populations to be interpreted in terms
of moles (the default), rather than molecules.
</li>
<li>
From this release forward, &appName; will be compiled with 
optimization enabled, before a new version is released.
</li>
<li>
Modified the CMDL (chemical model definition language) so that the
<code>log()</code> command has been changed to the <code>ln()</code>
command.  This was done for consistency with standard computer science 
notation, in which <code>ln()</code> represents the natural logarithm, 
and <code>log()</code> represents the logarithm base 10.
</li>
<li>
Added a new text field &quot;number of history bins&quot; to the
simulation launcher. This allows the user to control the number of
bins for storing the past values of a species that participates in a
delayed or multi-step reaction.  This field is only displayed if
the model contains a multi-step or delayed reaction.
</li>
<li>
Added a new command-line option &quot;<code>-numHistoryBins</code>&quot; 
to the command-line simulation runner, &quot;<code>runmodel</code>&quot;.
This option enables the specification of the number of bins that are to 
be used to store the past values of a species that participates in a delayed 
or multi-step reaction.  This value, if specified, is only used by the
simulation launcher if the model actually contains a delayed or multi-step
reaction.
</li>
<li>
Removed the parameter &quot;min num steps&quot; from the simulation
launcher; it has been replaced with the &quot;(step size
fractional)&quot; parameter.  This parameter specifies the initial
step size (as a fraction of the total time of the simulation) in the
case of a deterministic/ODE simulator, and it specifies the minimum
number ratio of the reaction time to the leap time, in the case of the
Tau-Leap simulators.
</li>
<li>
Added the option <code>testOnly</code> to the simulation launcher
program <code>runmodel</code>.  This option instructs the simulation
launcher to process the model definition file, validate the simulation 
parameters, and then exit.  It can be used to test a model and 
simulation parameters for correctness, without having to execute a
simulation.
</li>
<li>
Improved the efficiency of the delayed reaction solver, by halving
the amount of history information that needed to be stored regarding
each delayed reaction channel.
</li>
<li>
Modified the command-line simulation launcher program
<code>runmodel</code> to print out the average number of iterations
per second, during the last status statistics-collecting interval.
</li>
<li>
Fixed a serious inefficiency in the simulation engine, for the
case of models containing custom kinetic rate law expressions.  The
inefficiency was in the part of the engine that clears the cache
of previously computed expression values.  The cache was cleared for
all non-dynamic symbols, including those symbols (usually a majority)
that are not custom expressions (i.e., symbols that are bare numbers).
Modified the simulation engine so that only non-dynamic symbols 
which are in fact, expressions, have their value caches cleared.
</li>
<li>
Changed the "print" output type, to "table".  The "table"
output format now displays the simulation results in a resizable table
with individually resizable column widths.  Changed the "file" output
type to "store".
</li>
<li>
For the "table" and "store" output formats, floating-point values
are rounded to the correct number of significant digits, based on the
relative and absolute error tolerances specified for the simulator.
</li>
<li>
Modified the "plot" output format, so that the model name, simulator
alias, and date/time are now displayed in a label that is outside
the plot image.  When the plot image is saved, the labels will not
be saved with it, which is generally preferable because the desired
label format and font will differ based on the end application for
the plot.
</li>
<li>
Added a list of past simulations to the simulation launcher window.
This list can be used to go back and generate a plot, or tabulator view,
for the results of a previously run simulation.  The results of a
previously run simulation may be saved to a file as well.
</li>
<li>
The windows for simulation results plots and tabular views, are now
tiled in a cascading pattern together, rather than tiled independently.
</li>
<li>
Fixed a potential bug whereby the user was allowed to specify a 
relative error tolerance of greater than 1.0.
</li>
<li>
Modified the command-line simulation runner <code>runmodel</code>, so
that it prints out simulation results with a number of significant 
digits that is consistent with the specified absolute and relative
error tolerances.
</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.8.0/download.html">1.8.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.7.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.7.0</a></td>
<td>2004/06/08</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Modified &appName; to correctly implement the importing and simulation of
an SBML model for which the unit of &quot;substance&quot; is &quot;mole&quot;.
This fixes incorrect simulation behavior when an SBML model with
the default substance unit (&quot;mole&quot;) is imported.
</li>
<li>Fixed a bug that was causing an exception to be thrown in the
simulation launcher, when &appName; is deployed using Java Web
Start.</li> 
<li>Modified the simulation framework to model multi-step
reactions differently than delayed reactions.  Multi-step reactions
are now simulated using the Gamma Distribution as described by Gibson
and Bruck in their <em>Journal of Physical Chemistry A</em> paper (2000), while
delayed reactions are simulated using delay differential equations or
(in the case of a stochastic simulation) a time delayed stochastic
process.</li>
<li>Modified the SBML model export feature so that it correctly
preserves the units for &quot;substance&quot; that were originally
specified for the model.  This avoids a potential problem if a user
imports a model from SBML, and then exports the model back to SBML.</li>
<li>Decreased the maximum initial step size for the Dormand-Prince 5/4 ODE
solver, for the case of a model with a delayed or multistep reaction.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug whereby the &quot;tauleap-complex&quot; simulator was
giving an exception, when simulating a model imported from SBML, that
has local reaction parameters.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.7.0/download.html">1.7.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.6.4/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.6.4</a></td>
<td>2004/04/05</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed an inefficiency in the Gibson-Bruck simulator,
where reaction rates for reactions with custom reaction rate expressions, were
being recomputed after every iteration.  Now, a dependency tree is built of the 
reaction&apos;s rate expression.  The reaction rate is then recomputed only 
when one of the dynamical elements it is dependent upon, has changed.</li>
<li>Split the Tau-Leap simulator into two separate simulators, 
<code>taulea-complex</code> and <code>tauleap-simple</code>.  This allows for using
different algorithms for calculating the leap time, for complex and
simple models.</li>
<li>Made some speed improvements to the stochastic simulators, in the method
where the species populations are updated as a result of a reaction event.</li>
<li>Fixed a problem with the delayed reaction solver where the delay was artificially 
long in some cases.</li>
<li>Modified the <code>RegisterSBWSimulators</code> program so that
it prints out a message indicating that the simulators have been registered with
the SBW Broker.</li>
<li>Added a new program <code>LaunchSBWSimulators</code> that both
registers and launches the SBW interface to the simulators.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.6.4/download.html">1.6.4</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.6.3/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.6.3</a></td>
<td>2004/03/26</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed a bug in the SBML model reader, that was reported by Adam Margolin.  
This bug would cause an error in some cases, where
there are more boundary species than dynamical species in a model.</li>
<li>Improved the speed of the Gillesipe Tau-Leap
simulator, for large models with complex reaction rate expressions.</li>
<li>Made some speed improvements to the mathematical expression evaluation
engine, which will improve the performance for simulating models
with complex rate expressions, as well as the Gillespie Tau-Leap simulator.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.6.3/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.6.3</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.6.2/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.6.2</a></td>
<td>2004/03/22</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Implemented expression value caching for the deterministic simulators.
This improves simulation performance for complex models containing nested 
sub-expressions.  Slightly improved the speed of simulations of models
containing deferred-evaluation expressions.</li>
<li>Modified the stochastic simulators so that if the initial
value for a dynamic species is not an integer, the simulator 
will use the random number generator to select the nearest integer, 
in a weighted fashion, so that
on average the initial value is equal to the floating-point value specified.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in <code>runmodel</code> program,
such that the output file format specified on the command-line was being ignored.</li>
<li>Fixed a problem with the way that reaction rates were being computed,
for the rare corner-case of a fractional non-dynamic (boundary) species 
population, in the stochastic simulators.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.6.2/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.6.2</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.6.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.6.1</a></td>
<td>2004/03/12</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed some instability problems with the Gillespie Tau-Leap
stochastic simulator.</li>
<li>Made some speed improvements to the
Gillespie Tau-Leap stochastic simulator.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.6.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.6.1</a></td>
</tr>


<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.6.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.6.0</a></td>
<td>2004/03/10</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Added a new stochastic simulator &quot;<code>gillespie-tauleap</code>&quot;,
that can obtain an approximate solution of the chemical master equation,
according to an accuracy parameter that is specified by the user.  This
simulator is potentially faster than the &quot;<code>gillespie-direct</code>&quot;
simulator, because it can take large jumps in time, that will involve many
reaction steps, in one iteration of the simulator.</li>
<li>Added a feature whereby the &quot;<code>runmodel</code>&quot; program
is capable of computing the steady-state fluctuations of any of the
dynamical species in the model, as an optional post-simulation computation. 
This feature is activated using the optional 
&quot;<code>-computeFluctuations</code>&quot; command-line argument.</li>
<li>Made some speed improvements to the delayed reaction solver, for the
case of stochastic simulations.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug the chemical model definition language (CMDL) parser,
where a symbol defined within an included file, would never appear as a species
in the containing model, even if it is included as a participant in a reaction.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the deterministic ODE solvers, for the case of a model
with a delayed reaction with a large time delay, and a large 
<code>stopTime</code> parameter for the simulation.  In such cases, the
initial step size could be too large for the delayed reaction solver to
handle, which would cause the simulation to fail with an exception.</li>
<li>Fixed a problem in the simulation engine, that was causing stochastic 
simulations with a non-integer initial value for species populations,
to become unstable.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.6.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.6.0</a></td>
</tr>


<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.5.2/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.5.2</a></td>
<td>2004/02/25</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed a problem with the translation of CMDL (".dizzy") model
descriptions into SBML.  Kinetic Laws and other formulas are now
correctly output to SBML, with the species symbols in the formulas 
representing concentrations, rather than substance amounts.</li>
<li>Slightly improved performance by some code refactoring in
the simulation engine.</li>
<li>Fixed a problem whereby formulas in imported SBML models were not
being interpreted correctly by the simulator; species symbols
were not being interpreted as representing a concentration.</li>
<li>Fixed a problem with the <code>runmodel.sh</code> script; 
it was not working, due to changes to the SBML reader 
in the 1.5.0 release.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.5.2/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.5.2</a></td>
</tr>


<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.5.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.5.1</a></td>
<td>2004/02/24</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed several bugs in the behavior of the progress indicator
bar and the &quot;secs remaining&quot; text field, in the simulation
launcher frame.  The progress indicator and &quot;secs remaining&quot;
text field should now behave properly when the &quot;pause&quot;,
&quot;cancel&quot;, and &quot;resume&quot; buttons are used to 
control the simulation.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher frame so that the progress indicator
and the &quot;secs remaining&quot; text field are always visible, not
just when a simulation is running.  This reduces annoying flicker of
the user interface controls when a simulation starts and stops.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.5.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.5.1</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.5.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.5.0</a></td>
<td>2004/02/13</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Added a graphical progress bar and a text field indicating
the estimated number of seconds for the simulation to complete,
to the simulation launcher window.</li>
<li>Added the ability to the <code>runmodel</code> command-line
program, to print periodic status reports on the progress of
the simulation, to standard error (<code>stderr</code>).</li>
<li>Made several changes to the simulation engine and expression-evaluation
code, to improve the speed of simulations.</li>
<li>Removed redundant step in the implementations of the 
stochastic simulators (Gillespie and Gibson-Bruck), where
the expression value caches were being cleared twice.</li>
<li>Fixed a problem in the <code>jfreechart.jar</code> library, which
was causing &quot;class definition not found&quot; error messages
to be written to the console, upon start-up of the &appName; application.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.5.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.5.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.4.4/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.4.4</a></td>
<td>2004/02/10</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed a bug in the deterministic simulators based on the <code>OdeToJava</code> 
ODE solvers, in which the simulators were failing to delete the temporary file 
containing the simulation results.  This was cluttering up the temporary files 
directory with old (unneeded) data files.</li>
<li>Added a new launcher <code>runmodel</code> in the <code>bin</code> subdirectory
of the &appName; installation directory.  This launcher is designed to launch
the command-line interface to &appName;, without needing any prior user configuration.
</li>
<li>Simplified the <code>runmodel.sh</code> script, to make user configuration easier.</li>
<li>Removed the <code>runmodel.bat</code> script, because it is superseded by the
<code>runmodel</code> launcher.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.4.4/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.4.4</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.4.3/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.4.3</a></td>
<td>2004/02/06</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Created a new program &quot;<code>SimulationLauncherCommandLine</code>&quot;
that runs a simulation in batch mode, saving the results to a file that the user 
specifies.  The &quot;<code>runmodel.sh</code>&quot; and &quot;<code>runmodel.bat</code>&quot;
scripts now run this batch mode simulation program, instead of the old program 
that would open a simulation launcher window.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the command-line parsing for the &appName; command-line
applications &quot;<code>ModelLoaderApp</code>&quot; and
&quot;<code>SimulationLauncherCommandLine</code>&quot;, causing an error
when a very short command-line option is passed to the parser.</li>
<li>The &appName; application now prints out the total number of iterations
that occurred in the simulation, to the console window, after the simulation
completes.</li>
<li>The &quot;ensemble size&quot; and &quot;min number of time steps&quot; 
simulation parameters are now &quot;long&quot; integer parameters.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the <code>runmodel.bat</code> batch file.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.4.3/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.4.3</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.4.2/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.4.2</a></td>
<td>2004/02/05</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed a bug where if the user had made a change to the model definition 
editor buffer, and then selected &quot;Open...&quot; from the &quot;File&quot;
menu, the application would disregard the user&apos;s answer to the subsequent
confirmation dialog box.  If the user answered &quot;no&quot; to the prompt 
for whether to proceed, the application would still open the file and discard 
the previous edits to the buffer.</li>
<li>Modified the simulator engine to prevent huge unnecessary memory allocations 
when performing a stochastic of a models with an extremely large number of 
reactions and species.  This potentially improves performance in such cases by 
avoiding the use of large amounts of swap space on the disk drive.</li>
<li>Fixed a problem where the application was not properly handling the exceptional 
case of the system running out of memory during the initialization of a simulator.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher so that when the user clicks on the
&quot;start&quot; button, the response of the button control is immediate.  
In cases of very large and complex models and certain simulators (namely, 
&quot;<code>gibson-bruck</code>&quot;),
initialization was taking a long time, which was delaying the response of the 
button control.  Now, initialization of the simulator is performed in the
background, just prior to execution of the actual simulation.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher to rename the &quot;stop&quot; button 
to the &quot;pause&quot; button.</li>
<li>Changed the way that the deterministic simulators handle delayed
(or multi-step) reactions, to improve numerical stability and performance.</li>
<li>Modified the &quot;<code>odeToJava-dopr54-adaptive</code>&quot; simulator, so
that it is now possible to pause or cancel a running simulation within this simulator.</li>
<li>Removed support for the functions <code>gammaln()</code> and <code>rand()</code> in 
mathematical expressions.  The <code>rand()</code> function causes problems with
the expression value cachying feature introduced in version 1.4.0, and the
<code>gammaln()</code> code is likely encumbered with license issues.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.4.2/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.4.2</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.4.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.4.1</a></td>
<td>2004/02/02</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed a bug in the CMDL command language parser,
where an exception is thrown if an include directive occurs after a symbol definition.</li>
<li>Modified the CMDL command language parser
so that it gives a more comprehensible error message if the user attempts to define
a symbol name that is reserved for a default model element.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.4.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.4.1</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.4.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.4.0</a></td>
<td>2004/01/30</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>For complex models (many symbols defined as complex expressions), 
increased the speed of the stochastic simulators
by a factor of five.  Slightly improved the speed of the simulators 
for the case of simple models (all elementary
reactions, no custom reaction rates).</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher so that it remembers the directory
of the last output file selected, when the output type is &quot;File&quot;.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher so that the Cancel/Stop/Resume 
buttons are disabled in the OdeToJava simulators, which do
not allow interruption by the simulation launcher.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher so that different comma-separated-output
(CSV) output file formats are supported, for saving simulation results to a file.
Currently there are three options:  CSV-excel, CSV-gnuplot, and CSV-matlab.
The only difference currently is the choice of character that is used to designate
the &quot;comment&quot; line, which is the first line of the output file.  This
also makes it more clear that the choice of &quot;File&quot; output type, 
refers to a comma-separated-value file format.</li>
<li>Added a new &quot;view model in human-readable format&quot; feature which displays
a model description in &quot;human-readable&quot; format, in a dialog box.
Added an exporter plug-in so that it is possible to save the model description in the
same human-readable format to a file, using the &quot;Export&quot; menu item.</li>
<li>Modified the command language parser to fix a hard-to-understand error message 
that occurs when there is a syntax error inside nested loops.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher to permit the user to optionally specify a 
texual label that is added as a subtitle to the simulation results plot.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the on-line help search screen where the &quot;jump to next
search hit&quot; feature was not working for any searches after the first search.</li>
<li>Added a text area to the on-line help search screen, that explains the
&quot;jump to the next search hit&quot; feature.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.4.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.4.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.3.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.3.1</a></td>
<td>2004/01/27</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed a bug in the command language parser, which was causing
parser errors when a macro definition contains a loop construct.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the command language parser, which was causing
parser errors when a loop construct directly precedes a reaction definition statement.</li>
<li>Modified the command language parser to allow the value of
a symbol to be redefined, as long as the symbol has not been promoted to a
<code>Species</code>, <code>Reaction</code>, <code>Parameter</code>, or <code>Compartment</code>
at the point where the value of the symbol is redefined.  The purpose of this feature is
to permit the user to define a template definition with an &quot;output&quot; parameter.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.3.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.3.1</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.3.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.3.0</a></td>
<td>2004/01/26</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Added a template feature to the Chemical Model Definition Language (CMDL).</li>
<li>Improved the efficiency of the first pass of the command-language parser.  Improved
syntax error detection in the command-language parser.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the SBML parser where
it was not catching the case of a parameter defined without any value (or parameter rule) being provided.
This was leading to the application aborting unexpectedly, when a SBML file is loaded containing this
type of semantic error.</li>
<li>Added support to the SBML reader for reading an SBML model containing a reaction with an intrinsic 
time delay.  The <code>kineticLaw</code> must conform to a strict format rule.  The application
can now export (to SBML) a model containing a time delay, and read the model back into the simulator.</li>
<li>Improved error handling by adding debugging code to the console, in cases of 
exceptions.  The application should no longer abort when an unexpected exception occurs in processing
a model.</li>
<li>Modified the SBML writer so that it can properly export a model containing a reaction
with an intrinsic time delay.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.3.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.3.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.2.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.2.0</a></td>
<td>2004/01/13</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed the problem with the &appName; installer for the Mac OSX platform, where
the installed application launcher would crash with an &quot;unexpected error&quot;
dialog box message.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the layout of the simulation launcher control screen, where the 
full text of the &quot;select all&quot; button was not being displayed.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the simulation launcher 
where the simulation was not being cancelled, in the case where the user
selects too many symbols for displaying on a plot.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the chemical model definition language (CMDL) parser where the
application was aborting when the parser encountered a mathematical expression that 
has invalid syntax.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the chemical model definition language (CMDL) parser
where parsing errors in the model definition file were resulting in the exception class
name being unnecessarily included in the message part of the exception.</li>
<li>Changed the simulation results plotter so that the
vertical axis label is the more generally applicable &quot;value&quot; rather than 
&quot;populations&quot;.</li>
<li>Added a new Systems Biology Workbench (SBW) simulation service, for the 
Gibson-Bruck stochastic simulation algorithm.</li>
<li>Modified the &quot;Register SBW Simulators&quot; program so that it
registers services for all three supported simulators:  Gibson-Bruck, Gillespie,
and Deterministic.</li>
<li>Implemented a work-around for an InstallAnywhere bug, so that the &appName;
program now launches correctly when installed on a Mac OSX computer.</li>
<li>The InstallAnywhere installer for &appName; now logs error messages to a log file
&quot;<code>ins&appName;.log</code>&quot;.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug where the &quot;copy to clipboard&quot; button was failing to
be displayed in the simulation results plot window on the Windows platform,
in some cases.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug where selecting &quot;view in Cytoscape&quot; with a syntactically
incorrect model in the editor pane, leads to a <code>NullPointerException</code>.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug where models were not displaying correctly within Cytoscape, since
version 1.0.0.  This is because the Cytoscape SBML reader requires SBML Level 1, version 1.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug where the &quot;Save As...&quot; menu item was not being
enabled under the correct conditions (it should be enabled whenever the
editor buffer is not empty).</li>
<li>Fixed a bug where the &quot;Reload model&quot; feature was not working properly.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.2.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.2.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.1.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.1.1</a></td>
<td>2004/01/05</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Modified the delayed reaction solver so that the internal running
window average is recalculated from scratch, each time a minimum
number of points (default 4000) has been inserted into the queue.
</li>
<li>Fixed a file-loading bug pertaining to the case where the model 
builder fails to construct the model from the model definition file.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher to dump a stack backtrace to the 
terminal window if a low-level error condition is detected.</li>
<li>Generalized the multi-step reaction solver into a &quot;delayed&quot;
reaction solver, to permit phenomenological
modelling of reaction processes with an intrinsic time delay.</li>
<li>Changed the command language model builder to add language extensions
for specifying a multistep or delayed reaction.</li>
<li>Fixed bugs in the main editor window and the plot window,
where window resizing was not working correctly on the Windows platform.</li>
<li>Removed unnecessary label from main editor window, which was taking up 
space on the screen.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.1.1/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.1.1</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.1.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.1.0</a></td>
<td>2003/12/22</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Added a <code>reload</code> menu item, which is used for reloading the model
that is currently in the editor window, into the simulation launcher.  It replaces
the model that is currently loaded into the simulation launcher.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the simulation launcher, where it would still display a graph
even when the simulation was cancelled.</li>
<li>Made the simulation plot window dynamically resizable.</li>
<li>Made the main editor window dynamically resizable.</li>
<li>Added a hook to the simulation launcher so that an external application can 
dynamically replace the model loaded in the simulation launcher.</li>
<li>Added a hook to the simulation launcher so that an external application can
detect when a simulation starts or ends.</li>
<li>Fixed bug where the &appName; command language interpreter was
rejecting model definition files that ended with whitespace.</li>
<li>Added an &quot;append&quot; check-box to the simulation launcher
window, which allows for specifying that the output file should be appended to, rather than overwritten.</li>
<li>Added a &quot;save as PNG image&quot; button to the simulation results plot 
window, which is used to save the plot as a PNG image file.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher to display all symbols (not just species) 
in the list-box of symbols that can be displayed in the simulation results.</li>
<li>Modified the simulation launcher to allow for an external application to
hide the Output Type controls, and added a callback mechanism to return the simulation
results to the calling application using a queue data structure.</li>
<li>Added support for copying the simulation results plot image to the 
system clipboard, on operating systems that support image transfer to the
clipboard (e.g., Windows).</li>
<li>Added full-text search capability for the online application help.</li>
<li>The application help frame is now initially centered in the screen.</li>
<li>Added a &quot;select all symbols&quot; feature to the simulation launcher.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.1.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.1.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../1.0.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.0.0</a></td>
<td>2003/12/08</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Added new deterministic (ODE) simulators &appName;,
based on the &quot;odeToJava&quot; library for numerical solution of ODEs.  This library
includes a Dortmand-Prince 4/5 Runge-Kutta solver with adaptive step-size control, and
an implicit/explicit Runge-Kutta solver with adaptive step-size control (for models
with a high degree of stiffness).</li>
<li>Modified the SBML reader to permit inclusion of &quot;rules&quot; in SBML models</li>
<li>Modified the SBML writer to export models in SBML level 1, version 2.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in which the operation does not terminate, when model-building
fails after the user selects &quot;Export&quot; from the &quot;Tools&quot; menu.</li>
<li>Created separate fields in the SimulationLauncher
for specifying the matximum allowed relative and absolute errors</li>
<li>Fixed a bug for the case of a parameter defined as a deferred-evaluation
expression</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/1.0.0/&installerDownloadRelURL;">1.0.0</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../0.0.8/&installerDownloadRelURL;">0.0.8</a></td>
<td>2003/11/21</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Modified the fixed-stepsize deterministic simulator so that it can detect when the
simulation error exceeds a certain threshold, and produce a human-comprehensible 
error message (the message suggests that the step-size be decreased).</li>
<li>Modified the &quot;simulation launcher&quot; pane so that it has text-box controls
for specifying separate simulator-specific parameters, such as the ensemble size, the
minimum number of steps, and the maximum allowed fractional error.  Default values
are auto-filled in these new fields, depending on the type of simulator selected.  The
&quot;ensemble size&quot; and &quot;number of steps&quot; are now separate fields.</li>
<li>The &quot;plot&quot; output type no longer gives a strange error message when
a &quot;NaN&quot; (not-a-number) appears in the simulation output.  It now gives a more
human-comprehensible error message.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/0.0.8/&installerDownloadRelURL;">0.0.8</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../0.0.7/&installerDownloadRelURL;">0.0.7</a></td>
<td>2003/11/07</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Modified the editor pane so that it &quot;remembers&quot; the directory of the last file
that was opened; the default directory for the file chooser for the next &quot;open&quot; command,
is set to this directory.</li>
<li>Fixed a problem where the ISB and Bolouri Lab logo images were not displaying in the on-line
help screen, when the computer is not connected to the network.</li>
<li>Removed the table of contents from the HTML User Manual used in the on-line help (the JavaHelp
environment provides its own table of contents).</li>
<li>Adjusted the default vertical dimension of the editor pane for the model editor, to 40 characters.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/0.0.7/&installerDownloadRelURL;">0.0.7</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../0.0.6/&installerDownloadRelURL;">0.0.6</a></td>
<td>2003/10/22</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>In the &appName; simulation launcher form, made &quot;Plot&quot; the default output mode</li>
<li>Redefined how the stochastic simulators compute
reaction rates for dimerization reactions, for model interchangability with the ODE simulators.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/0.0.6/&installerDownloadRelURL;">0.0.6</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../0.0.5/&installerDownloadRelURL;">0.0.5</a></td>
<td>2003/10/20</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li>Fixed a bug in the Gibson-Bruck simulator, for the case of a boundary
reactant species.</li>
<li>Fixed a bug in the command-language parser, it can
now accept tabs as valid whitespace in the model definition file.</li>  
<li>The
SBML import feature can now process model definition files that conform to the
SBML Level 1, Version 2 specification.</li>  
<li>Fixed a bug in which &appName; would
fail to start, in the case where &appName; was installed in the top-level
directory of a Windows (or DOS) drive.</li> 
<li>Redefined how the stochastic simulators compute
reaction rates for dimerization reactions, for model interchangability with the ODE simulators.</li>
</ul>
</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/0.0.5/&installerDownloadRelURL;">0.0.5</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td><a href="../0.0.4/&installerDownloadRelURL;">0.0.4</a></td>
<td>2003/08/28</td>
<td>Modified the Cytoscape bridge to use JNLP, so Cytoscape does not have to be bundled with the application</td>
<td><a href="&javaURL;/0.0.4/&installerDownloadRelURL;">0.0.4</a></td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.3</td>
<td>2003/08/26</td>
<td>Added the ability to simulate a multistep chemical reaction as a single composite reaction</td>
<td>0.0.3</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.2</td>
<td>2003/08/06</td>
<td>Added the ability to display a model in a <a href="&cytoscapeURL;">Cytoscape</a> window.</td>
<td>0.0.2</td>
</tr>

<tr valign="top">
<td>0.0.1</td>
<td>2003/08/04</td>
<td>First version of the program.  It is an alpha version,
intended only for internal use at &mainAffiliation;.</td>
<td>0.0.1</td>
</tr>

</table>
</p>

</isb:document>
